Who Can Kill a Child ?
Russian troops have just finished liberating
the concentration camp of Auschwitz . The SS worked at top speed
to execute and burn the prisoners .
There where not enough ovens to do the job ,
so the bodies were burned in the open air .
The Polish people were allowed to enter the camp
to witness the atrocities that had taken place .
The prisoners were tattooed for later identification .
Some of them had been used for laboratory experiments ,
such as virus inoculation ,
implantation of cancerous cells , skin grafting , etc ...
Many of the children were singled out for these experiments .
On screen , we see one of them , who has had a trepanation performed
creating an irreversible loss of brain control .
These scenes , shot by the SS with their own cameras
demonstrate how the prisoners were forced to carry the bodies
of they 're own relatives , to the grave sites .
Faced with such an enormous quantity of victims ,
they were forced to use bulldozers .
Captured documents prove that at Auschwitz ,
almost one hundred thousand people perished .
Of these , 40000 were children , less than 14 years of age .
At the time of their liberation , only 2385 children were still alive .
The majority of them sicken by tuberculosis
or acute anemia , caused by lack of food and medical attention .
The civil war between India and Pakistan
killed over a million people .
The victims , were not only the result of the war alone ,
since a large nomadic population unable to find refuge ,
was herded into improvised concentration camps ,
in which there was insufficient food or water .
These scenes show the trucks that daily transported
the corpses of the aged and the children
to the common graves .
The help offered by the UN was not enough .
UNICEF points out that , int this corner of the world ,
one child dies every 5 seconds .
After 3 years and one month of fighting ,
the armistice was signed , the past July , 27th ,
putting and end to the Korean war .
With the peace , Korean orphans
have found shelter , protection and food ,
thanks to charitable American foundations
and the unconditional help of the government in Washington ,
which has build , on the outskirts of Seoul ,
hospitals and rehabilitation centers .
In these centers , the children are fed ,
taken care of , and rehabilitated physically ,
as well as psychologically .
They are taught to appreciate their worth ,
and even how to take part in sports .
With the war behind them , and thanks to this
humanitarian help , thousands of young Korean orphans
will learn how to face with optimism a future of peace .
The war continues in the Indochina peninsula .
In many of the cities of south Vietnam ,
demonstrations are directed against the government .
Grenades explode in the streets , cutting off the lives of
men , women and children .
The American army has brought into the country
almost half a million soldiers .
These forces , together with the strength of their
modern and efficient arms ,
will undoubtedly bring peace to southeast Asia .
Daily , American jets bomb military objectives .
Sometimes , however , as we see on the screen ,
the bombing affect the civilian population .
In the village of Tien Goa ,
hundreds of women and children where killed or set to fire
by napalm .
The civil war in Nigeria has been waging for 2 years .
Tribes from the south have completed their encirclement
of the Biafra region , the most affected by this conflict .
The population flees to the north ,
attempting to take refuge in primitive concentration camps .
But the meagerness of food and medical assistance ,
makes them an easy prey for death .
On top of all this , is the Spectre of a terrible drought
which , for 6 months , has afflicted Mauritania , Mali ,
Nigeria and Chad .
Over 11 million human beings face the threat of death ,
by starvation or by thirst .
The aid received is not enough ,
needed urgently is medical help and food .
As always , the most affected by the tragedy are the children .
The international red cross calculates that
up to the present , more than 300.000 children have died
from hunger , or dehydration .
She doesn 't seem to have drowned .
No ... check this ,
and here . These are wounds from a knife or small blade .
Here in the belly , another four .
She seems foreigner .
Maybe she was thrown out of a yacht ,
and then the tide brought her into the beach .
Look , she has further injuries on the thigh .
It must be the work of a madman .
Hey , wake up . Wake up .
It 's Benavís .
Pardon me , what 's happening ?
Oh , it 's Benavís 's big fiesta !
- Did you take that one ? - I 've got to get some more film .
- We 've got to find a hotel , first . - OK , up there .
Yes , come on .
Excuse me ... where can we find a room , only for tonight ?
No sir , I 'm sorry . In this time of the year we 're " Al Tope " .
" Tope " ?
Yes , sir , " Ilenos " ... full . Every hotel is full .
All of them ?
Yes , but go to this address , saying it 's from me .
It 's a private house , that rents rooms .
It 's in the old section of the city , you 'll love it !
It 's ... very typical !
- Gracias ! Good bye ! - Gracias ! Hey , is that what they say ?
- Yes , gracias . - Gracias !
- Hey look , what 's that ? - That 's called a pi ... " Piñata " .
I wish the children were here .
This is the only one I have .
Oh , wait .
Since it 's facing the street , it 's a bit noisy ,
but it has a lovely light .
Here it is .
- The bathroom is down the hall . - Yes ...
- Are you planning on staying long ? - Only for tonight .
How long ?
I 'm sorry .
" Una Sola Noche " ( Just one night )
And where are you going ?
We 're going to " Almanzora " .
Where ?
" Almanzora " island .
Ah , Almanzora .
Almanzora !
We 're here , at benavís , Almanzora is roughly ... here .
If you 're looking for quietness , here is where you 'll find it .
Tourism has not yet reached the island , it 's ...
4 hours away , on a boat .
Yes , I knew Almanzora twelve years ago .
- Where can I rent ? - " Alquilada " ?
- Rent , a boat ? - There 's a man that delivers
the mail ; He goes twice a week to Almanzora .
I prefer to rent a boat myself , to be able to go fishing and
sightseeing ... Yes !
Go to the port , and ask for Enrique Amoros .
He 's the one that takes the mail ,
and also rents boats to tourists .
- Enrique Amoros ... - Is your wife going with you ?
- Yes ! - I 'm asking due to her state ,
I believe there 's no doctor in Almanzora .
I 'm almost a doctor ... Biologist , " Biólogo " .
In that case there 's no problem !
- Do you want the paper ? - Yes , thanks !
- Gracias ! - Here to serve you , miss .
- I think benavís is lovely . - Ah , but I prefer Almanzora .
- Well I like benavís . - It 's too crowded , Evie .
To get to the sea , you 've got to walk over millions of people .
- Let me take a photograph . - Right .
Sit down , there . Wonderful .
How about that , all right ?
Oh , I need some more film .
- How may I be of help ? - Please , six cartridges for this camera .
- Color ? - Yes .
Tom , what 's this ?
Is almost over .
The sacrifice of the bozos as a
sign of protest for the war have been useless .
The remains of the Thai army , mingled with civilians , escape to
the Phuket port , trying to reach the American fleet boats ,
that will take them to Philippines .
Bangkok 's defense has been lifted , and an air bridge
has been established ,
for the evacuation of the capital , where chaos reigns .
The cadavers pile up , as UNICEF and the international red cross
beg for help for more than 30.000 children wounded or orphan .
With Thailand 's fall , it is said ...
- Six cartridges , was it not ? - Yes ...
The world is mad .
The worst is that the children are always the ones that suffer the most .
If there 's a war ... the children . If there 's hunger ... the children .
Niños ... is that children ?
- Yes . - What 's he saying about the children ?
- It 's nothing . - 1032 ' Pesetas ' .
- Thanks . - A good day to all , OK ?
Hey , where 're you going ?
Take a photograph of my first paddling in benavís .
It 's warm !
What did you say ?
Forget it !
What 's going on ?
I don 't know ...
Are you happy ?
- Are you happy ? - Yes !
- Where are all the Spaniards ? - I suppose they 're all in England !
Shall we sit down ?
Where ? It 's so crowded .
Well , we 're not helping this situation .
What 's the matter ?
Nothing .
What is the matter ?
Oh , nothing , nothing .
I was just looking at the sea ...
- Almanzora is ... - " Almanzóra " .
Ah , " Almanzóra " ...
Is just over the horizon , there .
What else ?
- What do you mean ? - There 's something else on your mind .
Well ... I was just thinking about what that
man in the photographic shop said .
That man is crazy ,
and the people who suffer most from his madness are ... kids .
Now that Thailand has fallen , Asia is in the hands of the communists ,
and a civil war starts because of Mao 's death .
Asia ... there 's no war here .
Yes , but there was a civil war once , in benavís , Evie ,
and it could happen again .
Do you remember ' la dolce vita ' ?
- ' La Dolce ' what ? - ' La Dolce Vita ' .
It was an Italian film .
There was a character in it , a man who was very wise
and peaceful , married , with two children .
Loved his wife , and ... no real problems .
And then one night he took a gun ,
shot his two children , then killed himself .
Why ?
I suppose , to save them from the world of the future .
You wanted to kill him .
We have to others already , Evie .
This one 's all right !
If it wasn 't for him , we wouldn 't be going to Almanzora .
Do you regret it ?
No , not now .
Killing your kids so they 're ...
Not made to suffer for the mistakes we make ?
What was the director 's name ?
Fellini .
- Italian ? - Yes !
Of course , a fascist , just like Mussolini .
They 're both crazy .
Good night !
- What 's that ? - More rockets .
You 're right .
About what ?
Almanzora will be better .
Here 's too noisy , too many people .
Good night .
It 's too noisy !
Two corpses show up on the coast line .
The motor was tuned two days ago . Do you know how to use it ?
Yes .
Ask him if it possible to find somewhere to stay .
Is it difficult ... to find a hotel in Almanzora ?
Well , there 's a hostel ... if you were on the island you ought to know it .
Its name is Pensión Estrella .
Since there 's no tourists there ... It 's always half empty !
Pass me the bag !
Give me your hand , madam .
No , not there . You go on the bow .
- Sorry , I don 't understand . - You must go in the front . On the bow .
- You must sit there . - Up there ?
Do you really know who to handle the motor ?
Sí , yes , of course , no problem .
Tell José at the bar that I 've
already received the grates of beer .
- Beer ? - No , never mind ...
Tomorrow when I 'll take the mail , I 'll see you at Almanzora !
There 's a good sea ... in 4 hours or a bit more you 'll be there !
OK !
Buenas Tardes !
Have a nice journey !
Darling , ' Tardes ' means afternoon ! You must say ' Buenos Días ! ' .
I 'm sorry ! Buenos Días !
I wish I could bathe .
Splash yourself a little .
It 's not the same !
The water 's so clear , you can see the bottom !
Look , a flower .
It must be from Almanzora .
The current often carries drift wood ,
palm leaves , things , all the way to the mainland .
I think we 're going to enjoy it there .
Look , there it is !
It certainly looks peaceful .
How can you tell that ?
Well , long after we left the mainland , you could still hear voices
and laughter from the beach .
But from here , it seems as if the island has been deserted .
All you can hear is the wind .
Manolo , give me a hand !
Be careful !
Grab it !
Very well !
Done !
Get her bag , please !
Thank you !
Come on , boys , let 's hit the water !
I 'm coming ! Let 's go , Manolo !
Hey , what are you trying to fish ?
What are you trying to fish ?
What do you use for bait ?
Tom , it 's so hot , lets go !
- I 'll race you ! - OK !
- Aren 't you coming ? - No .
- I should have bought a hat . - Well , we could buy one here .
- Eh ... - What ?
There 's nothing .
- Just the sea , seagulls ... - And the sun !
It 's so hot !
Madam , allow me to introduce you to ... The Plaza mayor .
It 's exactly as it was , twelve years ago .
Tom , what 's that ?
Uhm ? What 's what ? Oh , that 's an ice cream cart .
Oh , I 'd love an ice cream !
Hello ?
- There 's nobody there . - Oh never-mind .
Let 's just take one and leave the money .
OK .
It 's melted !
There 's a bar over there , come on .
There 's no one here , either .
It looks as if they left in rather a hurry .
It 's strange !
- No one 's been here for so long . - What do you mean ' for so long ' ?
Look , that 's been turning for hours .
Tom , I 'm so thirsty and hungry .
Well , let 's see what they 've got !
Now , to drink ...
there 's coke and ... beer .
And cold , too .
And to eat ,
well ,
all I can see is some sugar , and burned chicken !
I think there 's a shop outside .
Just to the left .
Should we go there ?
No , you go , it 's too hot and I 'm tired .
I 'll stay here .
Alright ...
Just as you like .
Good morning !
Hello .
Come in .
What 's your name ?
What 's your name ? 'Tu Nombre ... '
Lurdes ...
Ah , Lurdes ...
I have a baby here .
You day you might have a baby .
Please don 't go !
Please !
Please , come here .
Come .
Hello .
Hello ?
- Did you see anyone ? - No ...
Tom , it 's not possible !
Well , quite often the whole town celebrates some fiesta or other
and everybody goes to the other side of the island .
How about you ?
What do you mean ?
Did you see anyone ?
Yes , a little girl came here and then ran away .
Well , this is what I managed to get , bread , frankfurters , fruit ,
and some sardines .
- And a hat for you ... - Thank you .
And ...
A doll for Rosie ,
dressed in the local costume , of course !
Do you like it ?
What are we going to do , tom ?
Well , first we 're going to eat ,
and then we 're going to find that ' Pensión ' !
Please , come .
Come here !
Wait !
Wait a minute !
Come !
Must be people on the island , because if there are children , then ...
Who switched the power off ?
- What ? - The spit stopped turning !
I switched it off .
- Don 't you see what I mean , because ... - Our first meal in Almanzora .
Here , we have plates and everything else that we need ,
so , please , do follow me , madam !
And ...
Do sit .
There .
I will be your cook !
Your ...
Waiter ,
and now some paper napkins , and ...
It rang a few minutes ago , I answered it , but ...
They hung up .
Hello ?
'No Entiendo ' ... I don 't understand you !
Please , come here , please !
Do you speak English ? I don 't understand you !
Please , speak louder
in English or Spanish !
Hello ?
Who was it ?
- It sounded like a child 's voice . - Spanish ?
Well ...
German , Dutch , maybe even Swedish , I don 't know .
Tom , you said there were no phones on the island .
Well , there 's no direct link to the mainland , but ...
They may have installed a local exchange .
Well , at least we know we 're not the only people in the village .
Hello ?
Come ... come to ...
What it the same voice ?
Yes .
- What 's the population on this island ? - Oh , it 's about a 100 , maybe 200 .
And when they go away for these fiestas , can you remember ...
Well , did they always leave a village as deserted as this ?
It 's possible , I don 't know , I 've never stayed behind to find out !
They 're marvelous ' fiestas ' !
I mean , the people take along guitars , and they sing ... and ...
There aren 't any rockets !
What are you looking at ?
Nothing !
- Tom ? - Yep ?
Isn 't this it ?
Yes !
Come on .
Tom , there must be someone in this village .
What are we going to do ?
Simply wait .
Well , at least it 's cool in here . Someone is bound to turn up .
Is there a bath ?
What did you say ?
I 'm bade in sweat , I think I even smell a bit .
I 'd give anything for a shower .
Hey , there are other tourists on Almanzora .
Are they English ?
Dutch .
It 's a married couple and a girl .
Could it been a Dutch person ?
What ?
Well , the voice on the phone ,
you said it sounded like a boy speaking Dutch .
Where 're you going ?
The keys for 6 and 7 aren 't there ...
They might be upstairs .
Tom ,
come here , look !
I told you the village couldn 't be completely deserted .
There 's nobody there !
I 've just seen an old man , with a stick , going cross the road , look
into the doorway .
Well , look can 't you see his , his stick 's jutting out .
I 'll be right back !
Look , there 's a little girl .
Tom ! What is she doing ?
Stop it !
Oh my ...
Why have you done this ?
Why ?
Why you make ... that ?
Come back !
Come back here !
Hit him ! Hit him ! Hit him ! Hit him ! Hit him !
What happened , tom ?
There 's nothing .
- Tom ! - Nothing , nothing .
Look , tom , what happened ?
Look ,
the little girl was ...
Playing with the old man .
Playing ! ?
- And without , without ... - No , I saw her , I saw her hitting him ...
She was only playing , Evelyn , OK .
All right ?
Tom , you 're lying to me !
Tom , I saw how you carried the old man in your arms .
Now , what happened ?
The girl struck the old man and ...
She injured him .
- Then why didn 't you bring him here ? - Because I took him to his house .
You 're lying !
Look , Evelyn , I 'm telling you the truth ...
I took the old man home ,
it 's just down there , around the corner .
Look , tom , I saw how she hit the old man ,
I saw how you carried the man in your arms . Now ...
- Look , where is the girl ? - I left them both at home .
- Tom , will you stop lying to me ? - She cut his ...
forehead and it was bleeding a little .
- Tom . - That 's all .
Now , Evie , get a hold of yourself .
Look , there is something wrong on this island
and you 're trying to keep it from me .
If there is something wrong , then , whatever it is ,
I think we should leave .
Evelyn , I ...
Hello ? Hello ?
Hello ?
Yes ?
Could you speak more slowly ...
Are you ...
Are you Brit Van Der Holden ?
Tom , please don 't go up there !
It could be that girl .
Tom ?
Tom !
Don 't get any closer !
Please ...
Here ...
It 's too hot and you 're far to nervous , so try to rest , will you ?
You both need it .
I 'm going to have a talk to that man , OK ?
OK .
What 's happened in the island ?
I don 't know ...
I don 't know !
Please , calm down .
Feeling better ?
Thank you .
What 's happened in Almanzora ?
Yesterday night , around 11.30 pm ,
the voices started ,
and the laughter .
Laughter ?
Yes .
It was if all the children on the island had awaken .
They shouted ... And laughed .
They went in groups ...
And they entered the houses as if it was a party , but ...
But it wasn 't .
They entered ... And soon you could hear the screams .
Men and women screaming !
Then they would leave that house , and get into another ...
And another !
My wife went out on the street , to see what was going on ,
I remained at the window .
She left precisely when a body was leaving a house .
It seemed as though they were playing ...
But they carried knives , and sticks .
My wife started shouting ...
In my room I 've got a shotgun . I grabbed it ...
But I didn 't do anything .
No one in town did anything .
- Do you understand me ? - Yes .
Because ...
Who can kill a child ?
I was afraid , and hid on a small room
where we keep the bed linen .
I ..
I didn 't dare leave ,
until I heard your voices .
I don 't know anything else !
Nothing else !
Who hurt you ?
Myself , leaving my room ,
I stumbled and hit the floor .
Is it possible there are others alive on the island ?
I don 't know ...
In the north there 's more fishermen 's houses .
In the island 's centre , as well , there 's a couple of houses .
Only here in Almanzora .
- Feeling better ? - Yes , thank you .
Hello ?
Where are you ?
Please .
Help !
Please . Please .
Where are you ?
Hello , hello .
Please !
It 's cut off .
It 's the girl . The Dutch girl . Where can she be ?
She might be on public phones .
Where 's that ?
At the post office .
Post office ?
Yes , out of the guest house , on your left ,
about 100 meters away , on the first floor .
Right , you stay here with him .
I 'm going to find that girl , and then we 're leaving .
Come on , don 't be a fool !
Give it to me .
- Hold there . - OK .
The arm , take it .
Come on , let 's go ! Go !
Sir , the three of us must leave . Believe me .
Evie , we 're getting out of here ! The three of us .
- But why ? - I 'll tell you later .
Daddy , daddy !
Come !
Daddy , please , daddy , help me !
Aunt Isabel is sick . Daddy , please !
She 's at grandma 's house , and grandma is sick too !
They can 't breathe and I 'm really scared . They 've been hurt .
Daddy , please daddy , come with me , daddy , please .
Sir ... Please stay here .
She 's my daughter .
Let 's go .
Where are they going ?
Evelyn , I want you to do exactly as I tell you .
Tom , what 's going on ? What are all those shouts ?
Listen , we 're getting out of here , we 're going to run .
I know it 's going to be difficult for you
but we 've got to do it , do you understand ?
Yes , but tom ...
No matter what happens , even if it hurts you
we 've got to keep going .
Now , I want you to think of Richard and Rosie ,
and not on that baby inside of you .
Oh , for god 's sake , tom !
If you stumble , I 'll pick you up , but we 've got to keep going , all right ?
All right .
All right ... go !
I can 't ! Wait for me , tom !
Evie ! Evie , we must keep going ! Come on , we must keep going !
Listen , we must keep going . Come on ! We must keep going !
Now come on ! We must keep going !
No , please , no !
Run ! Come on , run ! Please Evie , come on !
Run !
They 're children ! They 're just little children !
What did the man at the 'Pensión ' tell you ?
Just that something strange had happened to the kids on the island .
Strange ? But what ?
I don 't know . Some sort of madness . I don 't understand this .
Where are we going now ?
There are a few houses , on the other side of the island .
We might be able to find a boat there .
Where are all the adults ? Where 's the people ?
Where are they , tom ?
There 's a boat near that house .
- But why don 't we get down there ? - There are children there .
Tom , what is happening to this children ?
I don 't know .
It just isn 't possible that all of them have gone mad .
And I don 't understand why they 've been attacking .
It 's as though they thought we adults were their enemies .
Perhaps the children of this island , guided by instinct ,
or by an evolutionary development , have started to ...
To what ?
Come on .
Good afternoon .
Did anything happen here last night ?
Last night ?
Is there someone else inside the house ?
Is something happening ?
Are there any other people living here ?
My mother and the children .
We need a boat to get to benavís .
Go to the port , on the other side of the island .
No , that 's not possible .
My husband and my brother-in-law have a fishing boat .
Where are they now ?
Out at sea , fishing . They 'll be back by sunset .
That boat 's no good , it has a hole in the bottom .
Tom , could you ask here for a glass of water , please ?
Do you have water , please ?
Yes , come in . Come inside .
Gracias .
How many months is she ?
Sorry ?
I don 't understand it .
Never mind .
Drink this and enjoy .
- What is she saying ? - Drink it , it 's tea .
Oh , thank you .
Hey , why are you bothering these people ?
Oh , these children !
Go and play on the beach for a while !
What a day they 're giving me today .
Please forgive them .
Are they your children ?
Yes , all four of them .
Hello !
Hello .
- Evelyn . - Yes ?
We 're going . Let 's get out of here .
Sir , wait !
They 're coming back . Sir !
Children , what are you doing ?
Come wash up , come on !
And you two , go on home now !
Well , didn 't you hear me ?
It 's just possible all the children of the village are coming here .
But tom , if we go back ...
We 'll cross through the village with the Jeep
without stopping until we reach that boat .
Whatever happens .
What do you mean ?
If we run into any of them ... Never mind .
Never mind what ?
We must reach that boat !
No , tom !
They 're leaving , Evie .
Nobody dared to attack a child to kill one of them .
That 's why they weren 't afraid , but ...
Now they are .
Tomorrow morning , Enrique and ...
Maybe some others
will reach the island and it will all be over .
There 's no one in sight .
Evie . Come lay down in there .
No !
Tom !
Do the children realize what they 're doing ?
I don 't know .
A normal child is incapable of killing an adult .
Well , I 'm a normal man , yet I ...
Managed to propose that we killed a child .
Stay and try to relax .
Just stay there , OK ?
OK .
Thank you .
Oh , tom !
Tom !
Evie , what 's wrong ? What 's happening ?
- What is it ? - Oh , help me , tom !
Oh help , me , please help me , tom , I can 't ...
I can 't stand it !
Lie down .
No ! It 's not that ! No , tom !
Please , you 've had a lot after all that 's happened .
You 'll be all right .
Evie , Evie , you will be all right , do you understand ?
It 's not that , tom , it 's ...
not the same as when Rosie and Richard ...
Help me tom .
I can 't stand it , please help me up !
No !
Tom , please feel it !
Could you feel it ?
Something ... Something inside me is moving !
Help me !
No , please .
- Please , I 've got to stand up ! - Evie !
Tom ...
he 's killing me .
What are you saying ?
I can feel it inside me . He 's ... He 's killing me !
Oh , they 're up there , they 're above us .
Can 't you hear them ? They 're laughing !
They 're laughing !
They 're laughing because they know that what I 'm carrying is ...
Tom ... tom he 's ...
He 's ... he 's ...
- Tom , he 's ... he 's one of them ! - No .
He 's killing me !
Tom ,
oh , tom ...
In the bar , a child ,
a little girl ...
She came , and ...
She touched me , tom .
I 'm sorry
she touched our baby !
He 's ... tom ... I 'm sorry ...
Where 's Rosie ?
Where 's Richard , tom ?
Oh tom ... I 'm sorry .
I 'm sorry tom , he 's ...
It 's them !
It 's them , sergeant !
It 's them , it 's them ! God !
It 's them !
Stop !
Help me !
Look at what this man did ...
Where are the town 's people ?
Bye !
- Hi , how 's it going ? - Hi !
Are you going to the mainland ?
- Yes . - Why don 't we all go ?
Because we 'd attract too
much attention in benavís . You 'll go later .
Do you think the children there will start playing the way we do ?
Yes , of course .
We are lots of children , all over the world .
Lots of them .